Until I entered high school two months ago, I didn't know...
The dampness of my uniform's hem, soaked by someone else's umbrella...
The warm body pressed up against my back...
The cool breeze of the air conditioner against my face...
Shinjuku... Shinjuku station...
Thank you for riding with us.
When I was little, the sky was closer... Much, much closer.
That's why I like the rain, since with it comes the smell of the sky.
And often, on rainy mornings, instead of transferring to the subway, I exit out the station gates.
June
Chocolate and... beer?
Here.
Thank you.
Um... have we met before?
No.
I'm sorry, my mistake.
It's okay.
Maybe it's fitting...
A faint clap of thunder
Clouded skies
Perhaps rain comes
If so, will you stay here with me?
The Garden of Words
This morning, the JMA has declared the start of the rainy season in Kyushu, five days earlier than average.
Nagasaki, Saga, Kumamoto, and Kagoshima prefectures expect strong rains over a wide area.
I'm home.
Welcome home.
I bought croquettes.
Great. Dinner will be ready soon.
Thanks.
Where's Ma?
Ran out.
Lucky us, we get all the croquettes to ourselves.
She left a letter saying not to go looking for her.
But maybe...
Leave her be.
I'm sure she'll be back after fighting with her boyfriend.
I've picked out a place. I'll be leaving next month.
Living alone?
With my girlfriend.
Don't think that's why Mom ran out?
You told her yesterday, right?
I wish she could just let her children go, you know?
She's the one who's making the rounds dating younger men.
Oh, yeah? Well then I'm gonna go live with my boyfriend!
She's got those youthful looks, after all.
That's 'cause she's never worked hard her a day in her life.
You're the one who's been piling on the years.
All done.
You do the dishes. I've aged enough.
Won't you be glad to have more space?
Suppose so.
Help me move, 'kay?
Sure.
Hey, have you heard of this?
What's this, a haiku?
It's a tanka.
As if.
Ask Ma when she gets back.
On sunny mornings, I transfer to the subway and head here, like I'm supposed to.
But I think to myself "This isn't what I should be doing right now. "
Rain...
Hi.
Hello.
Hey...
No school today?
And your office... Closed today?
I'm skipping work again.
And drinking beer in the park in the morning.
Drinking beer alone isn't good for your health.
You need to eat something with it.
You know a lot for a high schooler.
It's not me. My mom's the drinker.
I've got snack food.
Want some?
You just thought to yourself "This woman's a freak," didn't you?
No, I...
It's okay. We're human, after all.
We've all got our little quirks.
Maybe...
Definitely.
Okay, it's about time for me to go.
Heading to school now?
I've decided to only skip school on rainy mornings.
Well, we might see each other again.
Maybe when it's raining.
It was the first day of Kanto's rainy season.
A shoemaker?
I know it seems out of touch,
but I enjoy creating designs and making shoes.
Of course, I'm still terrible at it.
Of course...
But despite it all, I want to make it my career... if I can.
I've never told anyone this before.
Do you have any idea how late you are?
You know why I've called you here, right?
Hey...
Evenings, before I went to sleep...
Mornings, in the moment I woke up...
I realized I was praying for rain.
I realized that on sunny days, I was in a terrible, childish place,
with nothing but impatience.
She exists in a world of working adults, so very far away from me.
To me, she represents nothing less than the very secrets of the world.
Honestly, there are only two things I know for sure.
One: she must think a 15-year-old like me is just a little kid.
And two: making shoes is the only thing that will lead me away from here.
Please stay behind the yellow line for your safety.
Please be careful of the closing doors.
Good morning.
I thought you might not come today.
It's a miracle you haven't been fired yet.
Wow! Is that a shoe design?
Hey!
I can't see?
It's not something worth showing.
Really?
Yes, really!
Come on, sit down over there.
I'm going to eat breakfast. Would you like to join me?
Thanks, but I brought my own.
You made it yourself?
What? I cook sometimes, for your information.
Oh?
Then let's make a trade.
Wait, I'm not really that good a...
cook, you know.
It's your own fault.
That's a side of you I didn't expect.
What?
Sorry. But it's tasty in its own way.
It's got bite.
Don't patronize me.
Can I have another?
Hurry up!
Wait, bro!
Takao, be careful.
Happy birthday, Mom!
Thank you.
What could the three of you have gotten me?
Hey...
Do you think it's too late for me?
And you know what? I could actually taste the food.
So your taste disorder has improved?
I wouldn't go that far.
But just a little while ago, all I could taste was alcohol and chocolate.
I think you deciding to just quit was really for the best.
Maybe so.
You speak to me so gently,
like you're touching something fragile.
But back then, when I found it hard to even breathe,
you only listened to the voices around you.
You didn't believe me.
Then we'll start the paperwork for you leaving after the holiday.
I'll notify the higher-ups.
Okay. Sorry to cause you all this trouble even after we split up.
I'm glad, really...
About that old woman you met.
You know, the one you keep talking about who brings her lunch box to the park.
It seems like you've really struck a chord.
Yeah, get some rest.
Mr. Itou
Ever since then,
I've been
nothing but lies.
Rain...
It's raining again today in Kanto.
Here at Shinjuku Station's south exit, the commuters all have umbrellas in their hands.
July
Here, this is for you.
For me?
I've always ended up eating your food, see...
And you said you wanted it, right?
This book isn't cheap.
Thank you... very much.
It's my pleasure.
Um...
I'm actually making a pair of shoes right now.
Wow... A pair for yourself?
I haven't decided who they're for yet...
They're women's shoes.
But I haven't been able to get them right, and...
You know...
before I knew it, I wasn't able to walk properly anymore.
Are you talking about your job?
Yeah...
About a lot of things.
I don't know anything about her.
Her job, her age... what worries she carries...
Not even her name.
And yet I can't help but be charmed by her.
The rainy season is officially over ten days later than normal in the Kanto region.
The current temperature in the city is 26 degrees.
Like someone just flicked a switch, the sunny days came one after another.
Oh sure, now I think to myself "I'm glad that he's not skipping class anymore."
But in reality...
I wish the rainy season
had never ended.
This park sure is big.
I can't believe we're in Shinjuku.
Oh, pardon us.
Go ahead.
This is the Japanese gardens, right?
Where should we go next?
Isn't there a greenhouse? Let's check it out.
Yeah, let's.
It's like a totally different place on sunny days.
Thanks for the help.
Hey, why don't you eat dinner with us, Takao?
Sorry, but I've got my part-time job today.
This late?
And I don't want to impose.
The opposite! I'm going to be living with him from now on, so just this once...
I can hear you.
Well then, see you later.
He's a cute kid.
Did you notice his shoes?
They're handmade.
What? Seriously?
Just some ugly moccasins, though.
He's got a bright future, doesn't he?
I wonder if he'd make shoes for me?
Who knows? Teenagers' interests change on a whim...
My brother moved out, and the rainless days continued.
I had no excuse to head to that place.
And then, it was summer vacation.
August
I worked part-time almost every day over the summer.
Hmm, maybe chicken with cashew nuts?
Looks good to me.
We'll order it.
I wanted to earn what I could for tuition to a vocational school.
Tools and leather cost money too.
Sure, I missed her, but...
I think it's clinging to those feelings that's keeping me a little kid.
That's why I've decided to make shoes that will make her want to get up and walk.
What will the weather be like tomorrow?
I'm twenty-seven, but I don't feel any smarter than I did twelve years ago.
I've always been here, stuck in the same place.
September
It's just like Tsukishima to have got that confused for a week!
English class is no big deal.
That's cause Kiso's a pushover.
Akizuki!
Hey, long time no see.
Looks like you guys got a tan.
Yeah, we went to the beach a bunch.
You're still as pale as ever.
What'd you do over summer break?
Worked the whole time.
The whole time?
That's a lonely way to spend your high school days.
School, job, chores. School, job, chores.
I skip school sometimes!
Now that you mention it, you are late a lot, Akizuki.
Yep, this guy never shows up for 1st period when it rains.
I've got a condition where I can't ride the subway on rainy mornings.
Whatever, weirdo.
Teacher's Office
Ms. Yukino?
Ms. Yukino!
Satou...
Ms. Yukino...
Satou, save it for later.
Ms. Yukino!
Same goes for the rest of you.
I'm sorry, everyone.
I'll be here until after 5th period. After that, I'd be happy to.
Yukino came to school?
You didn't hear about her quittin'?
No. I didn't even know who she is.
You have old man Takehara for lit, right?
Yukino was always having trouble with the third-year girls.
Yeah, but Ms. Yukino didn't do anything wrong.
Someone's boyfriend fell for Ms. Yukino,
and as payback everyone in the class treated her terribly.
They spread so many rumors even her parents heard about them.
It went so far she couldn't come to school anymore.
Yukino's just too kind.
She should've brought it straight to the police.
We told Mr. Itou over and over!
But he didn't want to make a mess for the school in public.
Hey, what's the matter?
Those upperclassmen...
Do you know their names?
Ms. Yukino!
He totally sucks at it.
You're so cruel.
But man, you sure go through 'em.
What do you want, frosh?
Are you the third year, Aizawa?
An admirer?
Who the hell are you?
It seems like Ms. Yukino is quitting.
Huh?
Like I care about what happens to that slutty hag.
Who does this guy think he is?
Huh? What's this?
What's your deal?
Let's go tell a teacher...
Never seen this kid before.
Who are you?
Fallen for that old hag?
What a creep! Does he even know how old she is?
Poor guy. She must've tricked him.
She might go for him now, though.
Since she ain't a teacher no more.
Damn straight.
You should thank us.
I'm waiting for the rain.
A faint clap of thunder
Even if rain comes not
I will stay here
Together with you
Yes, that's the correct answer.
That's the right response to the tanka I told you when we first met.
If it rains, I wonder if you will be staying here?
In response to that verse, I answer...
Even if it doesn't rain, I will be here.
It was in the classic Japanese literature textbook.
Ms. Yukino...
I'm sorry...
I thought you would realize I was a classic literature teacher.
I mean, everyone at school knows about me.
But you're always off in your own little world, aren't you?
Hey, what happened to your face?
I was acting like you and drank too much beer.
Then I tripped and fell on the Yamanote line platform.
Oh, my!
Just kidding.
I got in a fight, that's all.
Look... It looks like we just swam across the river.
I think this might...
this might be...
...the happiest...
time of my life.
Yukino...
Yes?
I think I've fallen in love with you.
Not Yukino.
Ms. Yukino, remember?
I'm going to be moving next week.
Back to my hometown in Shikoku.
I made the decision a while back.
I was practicing how to walk on my own, there in that place.
Even if I'm barefoot...
So then...
So I want to thank you for everything, Akizuki.
Um, thank you for lending me these clothes.
I'll get changed now.
But yours aren't ...
Excuse me...
I'm going home.
Thank you for your hospitality.
I made this lunch for myself, but I made too much.
So if you'd like...
I haven't decided who they're for yet...
They're women's shoes.
I was acting like you and drank too much beer.
Then I tripped and fell on the Yamanote line platform.
A faint clap of thunder
Even if rain comes not
I will stay here
Together with you
Um...
Yukino,
please forget what I said earlier.
I was wrong... I hate you after all.
Ever since we first met, you struck me...
like a person I should avoid.
Drinking beer in the morning, spouting off some random tanka at me...
All day long you listen to other people talking,
yet never say a peep about yourself...
You knew I was a student, didn't you?
That's completely unfair!
If I'd known you were a teacher, I would've never told you about the shoes.
After all, you think I'll never amount to anything!
So why didn't you say anything to me?
You thought maybe you'd humor the little kid's fantasies for a while?
Tell me I'll never live up to my expectations!
Tell me I'll never measure up to my dreams!
You knew from the very beginning!
So tell me, god damn it!
Tell me I'm in your way!
Tell me that little kids should run along to school!
Tell me that you hate me!
You...
You're always like that.
You never say what's important,
pretending that it's not your problem and live on like that
all alone!
Every morning!
Every morning I put on my suit to go to school...
But I was scared...
I just couldn't go...
In that place...
You...
saved me!
I lived on with feelings frozen
Never expressed in words
And I clumsily held you in my arms on a rainy night
Street flyers and broken lamps
Everybody was rushing back and forth
It's not you but me who is to blame
I couldn't hide my own impulsiveness
Lady, you started running through a deserted station
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
The sight of you splashing through puddles disappears
Morning comes quicker in the back alleys
So I have to get hold of you now
To say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
Summer ended, and it came time to switch to our winter uniforms.
I got terrible grades on my finals.
I wasted who knows how many pieces of expensive leather.
I worked part-time over winter break as well.
And every time I added a layer to my clothing,
I wondered to myself how she was doing.
I don't have enough strength anymore
To grab onto the sky that's welled up with tears
You're strong enough not to feel hurt because of my unchanging heart
Lady, all wet from the rain, you looked into my eyes for a moment
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
Whistling, I walk after you
Even though I came to know a side of you I wasn't interested in
Just like the night we first fought
I say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
When I head out the gates and my shirt's shoulders are dry
It no longer rains much in your town
Only today continues into tomorrow
That's how you and I can never end
Lady, even now you still
Don't even open up a little umbrella
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
The sight of you splashing through puddles disappears
Morning comes quicker in the back alleys, so I have to get hold of you now
To say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
Unconcerned about getting soaked from the pouring rain
Whistling, I walk after you
Even though I came to know a side of you I wasn't interested in
Just like the night we first fought
I say, "Don't go away, don't go away"
This letter has gotten quite long without me even realizing it.
Thanks so much for reading it all. I hope you're doing well, Akizuki.
I hope the warm days of spring come soon.
Yukari Yukino
I was practicing how to walk too.
That's what I think now.
One day, when I can walk much farther on my own...
I'll go see her.